D = hY/2y * cot (A/2)

Where the constants used are:
h = the actual distance between the laser pointer and the optical axis of the camera. (93mm)
Y = total number of pixels along the y-axis (272)
A = angle of view of the camera (63)
Lens: Wide-angle lens F2.8 f = 28mm (35mm equivalent)


As these values are constants, we obtain,
D α 1/y
Or, D = k/y (where k is the proportionality constant for all the constants used above)

We used an experimental approach to determine the value of k. We wrote a simple program in C# to do the entire image processing work and for finding the position of the laser dot in the scene. We calibrated the apparatus by placing an obstacle at known distances from the center of the camera and noting down the number of pixels the laser dot is from the center of the image along the y-axis. After taking several readings, we obtained the value of k. 